<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Clemens Ager</title>
    <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Clemens Ager</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>Clemens Ager, Brixlegg</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/project/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Exhaled acetone dependency on inhalation</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/project/acetone-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/project/acetone-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exhaled concentration of inert gases simply depends on the inhaled
concentration.  Especially in steady state it is obvious that exhaled
concentration needs to be equal to the inhaled concentration.  In the
case of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) that take part in the
metabolism the relationship becomes more complicated.  The exhaled
concentration then also depends on metabolic production and
metabolization rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consider the concentration in steady state.  We already know that
exhaled concentration is a linear function of inhaled concentration,
fully described by two numbers - slope and intercept.  Based on a PBPK
model we derive the corresponding functions and discuss the influence
of physiological parameter on these numbers.  We also intend to
estimate these parameter based on recorded measurements.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metabolization of deuterated ethanol</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/project/d6ethanol/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/project/d6ethanol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although deuterated molecules appear in nature the full deuteration
appear only at practically non-detectable level.  These molecules are
therefore not of endogenous origin.  Considering safety deuterium is
not radioactive and behaves chemically like regular hydrogene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the metabolic pathway for ethanol degradation being well understood its
parameter are not easy to measure.  The main reason is that these
pathways are also permanently active in other metabolic contexts.
Therefore observing deuterated molecules not appearing in nature and
their metabolites is a promising method for observation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
