<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sci on C. Ager</title>
    <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/tags/sci/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sci on C. Ager</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Clemens Ager, Brixlegg</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2017 11:08:13 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://bdcaf.github.io/tags/sci/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>ERJ accepted correspondence</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/02/21/erj-accepted-correspondence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2017 11:08:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/02/21/erj-accepted-correspondence/</guid>
      <description>Nice the ERJ has accepted our correspondence about the future of respiratory medicine. Hope I will have the link soon.
Unfortunately I had extremely limited room to address the statistical issues. Anyway writing this correspondence was a pleasant experience. Really hope we will have more to say soon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>After three months finally an Euler result again</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/01/14/after-three-months-finally-an-euler-result-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2017 10:14:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/01/14/after-three-months-finally-an-euler-result-again/</guid>
      <description>Having spent three months on and off a problem I finally managed to sufficiently solve Problem 110. Strange how problems change once you work on huge numbers.
But now I can again proudly present my score . Nicely this puts me in the statistics of active ones on place 19 in Austria.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WTF - LOQ</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/01/11/wtf-loq/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 13:53:20 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/01/11/wtf-loq/</guid>
      <description>Just got Imputing defensible values for left-censored ‘below level of quantitation’ (LoQ) biomarker measurements forwarded. It starts as interesting read stating the problem but IMHO ultimatively fails to address the problem. I am especially disappointed that neither the IUPAC definition and guidelines are mentioned, nor the current ISO 11843. Especially the works of Lloyd A. Currie offer great insight in this topic.
The whole idea of censoring values below LOQ was already debunked by Currie.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nach der Konferenz</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/2016/09/17/nach-der-konferenz/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2016 16:48:41 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/2016/09/17/nach-der-konferenz/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alles wieder vorbei.  Für mich interessant waren von den Japanern ein
Experiment bei dem CO während einem Ergometerexperiment gemessen
wurden und ein chinesisches Experiment bei dem die Luft in einem
Airliner beobachtet wurde.  Interessanterweise haben die Chinesen auch
ein Paper über automatische GC/MS Auswertung gebracht.  Beides
Steckenpferde von mir.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>