<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Game on bdcaf</title><link>https://bdcaf.github.io/tags/game/</link><description>Recent content in Game on bdcaf</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 09:43:37 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bdcaf.github.io/tags/game/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Keep talking and nobody explodes</title><link>https://bdcaf.github.io/post/links/keep_talking/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2018 12:58:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/post/links/keep_talking/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;At the current &lt;a href="https://www.humblebundle.com/games/humble-indie-bundle-19"&gt;HUMBLE INDIE BUNDLE 19&lt;/a&gt; they
include the party game &lt;a href="http://www.keeptalkinggame.com"&gt;Keep talking and nobody explodes&lt;/a&gt;. One can get it the next 10
days for about 5€. Basically one sits in front of the computer which
simulates a bomb, the rest of the group has the bomb manual and is not
allowed to see the bomb. They need to talk the one on the bomb trough
defusal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t resist. Looking forward to try it at the next party.
Before I was watching some Youtube videos and it looks great fun.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Kerbal Space Program</title><link>https://bdcaf.github.io/post/links/kerbal/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2018 14:50:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/post/links/kerbal/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;These days I started up &lt;a href="https://kerbalspaceprogram.com/en/"&gt;Kerbal Space
Program&lt;/a&gt;. It is a space game
where you construct your own vehicles and explore the solar system.
As physics games go it is amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless you carefully plan out maneuvers they will lead to disaster -
which is often also hilarious to watch play out. Even getting into
orbit is a challenge in the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://bdcaf.github.io/post/links/2018-01-kerbal.jpg"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
 &lt;h4&gt;My first Mun landing without breaking stuff.&lt;/h4&gt;
 &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only critic point would be that one needs to learn about most
concepts outside the game. These may be small things like how the
solid fuel boosters are different from rocket engines - the boosters
can not be throttled, while the rocket engines can be. To the more
advanced topics of how to do orbit transfers and gravity assists.
Though once the concepts are understood it is immensely gratifying to
be able to these maneuvers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Wieder mal spielen...</title><link>https://bdcaf.github.io/post/2014/2014-01-14-wieder-mal-spielen/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2014 07:17:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/post/2014/2014-01-14-wieder-mal-spielen/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hab jetzt den &lt;a href="http://www.surgeonsimulator2013.com"&gt;Surgeon Simulator&lt;/a&gt; am laufen. Ist im &lt;a href="https://www.humblebundle.com/"&gt;Humble Indie Bundle X (pay what you want and help charity)&lt;/a&gt; grad zu kaufen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Macht viel Spaß. Schaut euch nur die YouTube lets plays an&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>