<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Git on C. Ager</title>
    <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/tags/git/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Git on C. Ager</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Clemens Ager, Brixlegg</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2018 11:24:39 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://bdcaf.github.io/tags/git/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>pretty git exercises</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/2018/02/14/pretty-git-exercises/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2018 11:24:39 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/2018/02/14/pretty-git-exercises/</guid>
      <description>I probably mentioned I use git for managing my code. Even in the simplistic way I know - already helpful. Like in this xkcd  It is not easy finding good exercises to improve.
I got pointed to learngitbranching. It looks polished and the exercises are short enough to do between. Just somehow I overlooked the commandos reset and undo to restart the exercised.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nice stuff from uibk</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/04/22/nice-stuff-from-uibk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2017 10:54:55 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/04/22/nice-stuff-from-uibk/</guid>
      <description>As I was checking whether the uibk would offer us some storage for git projects I was positively surprised they run a full gitlab instance.
Unfortunately we will be limited to 50 projects - so I will not be able to abandon my bitbucket account. Anyway nice to be able to host potentially sensitive stuff internal.
Also they run mattermost - now that looks very interesting. Chatting without going through american services&amp;hellip; Need to get my friends in there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publishing work flow template</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/03/03/publishing-work-flow-template/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2017 11:20:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/03/03/publishing-work-flow-template/</guid>
      <description>After some time my cookiecutter templates for my data analysis work flow is finally in a state that I can show the world. You can get it from github. All in all it is my way to setup a reproducible research work flow - for too long I have just copied files around.
It is all about using external tools in addition to R. The most essential being make. I am very proud about the makefile that keeps code and data directories clean.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>