<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Coauthoreds on Clemens Ager</title>
    <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Coauthoreds on Clemens Ager</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>Clemens Ager, Brixlegg</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/coauthored/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>test</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Filipiak, Wojciech and Beer, Ronny and Sponring, Andreas and Filipiak, Anna and Ager, Clemens and Schiefecker, Alois and Lanthaler, Simon and Helbok, Raimund and Nagl, Markus and Troppmair, Jakob and Amann, Anton (2015),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://stacks.iop.org/1752-7163/9/i=1/a=016004?key=crossref.798f068dedadbc97df4cca8b842a921c&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Breath analysis for in vivo detection of pathogens related to ventilator-associated pneumonia in intensive care patients: a prospective pilot study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;Journal of Breath Research (9)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.&lt;sup&gt;1088&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;1752&lt;/sub&gt;-7155/9/1/016004&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breath analysis for in vivo detection of pathogens related to ventilator-associated pneumonia in intensive care patients: A prospective pilot study</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2015a/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2015 10:36:21 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2015a/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/270513085_Breath_analysis_for_in_vivo_detection_of_pathogens_related_to_ventilator-associated_pneumonia_in_intensive_care_patients_A_prospective_pilot_study&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;research gate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wojciech Filipiak, Ronny Beer , Andreas Sponring , Anna Filipiak, Clemens Ager, Alois Schiefecker, Simon Lanthaler , Raimund Helbok , Markus Nagl , Jakob Troppmair and Anton Amann&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Existing methods for the early detection of infections in mechanically ventilated (MV) patients at intensive care units (ICUs) are unsatisfactory. Here we present an exploratory study assessing the feasibility of breath VOC analyses for the non-invasive detection of pathogens in the lower respiratory tract of ventilated patients. An open uncontrolled clinical pilot study was performed by enrolling 28 mechanically ventilated (MV) patients with severe intracranial disease, being at risk for the development of or already with confirmed ventilation-associated pneumonia (VAP). The recently developed sampling technique enabled the collection of breath gas with a maximized contribution of alveolar air directly from the respiratory circuit under continuous capnography control, adsorptive preconcentration and final analysis by means of gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS). VAP was confirmed in &lt;sup&gt;22&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;28&lt;/sub&gt; preselected patients (78%). The most common microorganisms were Staphylococcus aureus (&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;22&lt;/sub&gt; VAP patients), Escherichia coli (&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;22&lt;/sub&gt; VAP patients) and Candida spp . (&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;22&lt;/sub&gt; VAP patients). &lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;32&lt;/sub&gt; metabolites released by S. aureus in our previous in vitro studies were also detected in the end-tidal air of VAP patients infected with this pathogen. A similar overlap was seen in Candida albicans infections (&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;29&lt;/sub&gt; VOCs). Moreover, the concentration profile of selected compounds correlated with the course of the infection. This prospective pilot study provides proof of the concept that the appearance and the concentration profile of pathogen-derived metabolites (elucidated from in vitro experiments) in the breath of ventilated patients during clinically confirmed VAP correlates with the presence of a particular pathogen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breath analysis for in vivo detection of pathogens related to ventilator-associated pneumonia in intensive care patients: a prospective pilot study</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Filipiak, Wojciech and Beer, Ronny and Sponring, Andreas and Filipiak, Anna and Ager, Clemens and Schiefecker, Alois and Lanthaler, Simon and Helbok, Raimund and Nagl, Markus and Troppmair, Jakob and Amann, Anton (2015),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://stacks.iop.org/1752-7163/9/i=1/a=016004?key=crossref.798f068dedadbc97df4cca8b842a921c&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Breath analysis for in vivo detection of pathogens related to ventilator-associated pneumonia in intensive care patients: a prospective pilot study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;Journal of Breath Research (9)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.&lt;sup&gt;1088&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;1752&lt;/sub&gt;-7155/9/1/016004&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative analyses of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) from patients, tumors and transformed cell lines for the validation of lung cancer-derived breath markers.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Filipiak, Wojciech and Filipiak, Anna and Sponring, Andreas and Schmid, Thomas and Zelger, Bettina and Ager, Clemens and Klodzinska, Ewa and Denz, Hubert and Pizzini, Alex and Lucciarini, Paolo and Jamnig, Herbert and Troppmair, Jakob and Amann, Anton (2014),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24862102&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Comparative analyses of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) from patients, tumors and transformed cell lines for the validation of lung cancer-derived breath markers.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;Journal of breath research (8)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.&lt;sup&gt;1088&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;1752&lt;/sub&gt;-7155/8/2/027111&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breath analysis for the purpose of non-invasive diagnosis of lung cancer has yielded numerous candidate compounds with still questionable clinical relevance. To arrive at suitable volatile organic compounds our approach combined the analysis of different sources: isolated tumor samples compared to healthy lung tissues, and exhaled breath from lung cancer patients and healthy controls. Candidate compounds were further compared to substances previously identified in the comparison of transformed and normal lung epithelial cell lines. For human studies, a breath sampling device was developed enabling automated and CO2-controlled collection of the end-tidal air. All samples were first preconcentrated on multibed sorption tubes and analyzed with gas chromatography mass spectrometry (GC-MS). Significantly (p &amp;lt; 0.05) higher concentrations in all three types of cancer samples studied were observed for ethanol and n-octane. Additional metabolites (inter alia 2-methylpentane, n-hexane) significantly released by lung cancer cells were observed at higher levels in cancer lung tissues and breath samples (compared to respective healthy controls) with statistical significance (p &amp;lt; 0.05) only in breath samples. The results obtained confirmed the cancer-related origin of volatile metabolites, e.g. ethanol and octane that were both detected at significantly (p &amp;lt; 0.05) elevated concentrations in all three kinds of cancer samples studied. This work is an important step towards identification of volatile breath markers of lung cancer through the demonstration of cancer-related origin of certain volatile metabolites.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ABA-Cloud: support for collaborative breath research.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/elsayed2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/elsayed2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elsayed, Ibrahim and Ludescher, Thomas and King, Julian and Ager, Clemens and Trosin, Michael and Senocak, Uygar and Brezany, Peter and Feilhauer, Thomas and Amann, Anton (2013),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23619467&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ABA-Cloud: support for collaborative breath research.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;Journal of breath research (7)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.&lt;sup&gt;1088&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;1752&lt;/sub&gt;-7155/7/2/026007&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper introduces the advanced breath analysis (ABA) platform, an innovative scientific research platform for the entire breath research domain. Within the ABA project, we are investigating novel data management concepts and semantic web technologies to document breath analysis studies for the long run as well as to enable their full automatic reproducibility. We propose several concept taxonomies (a hierarchical order of terms from a glossary of terms), which can be seen as a first step toward the definition of conceptualized terms commonly used by the international community of breath researchers. They build the basis for the development of an ontology (a concept from computer science used for communication between machines and/or humans and representation and reuse of knowledge) dedicated to breath research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative analyses of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) from patients, tumors and transformed cell lines for the validation of lung cancer-derived breath markers.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Filipiak, Wojciech and Filipiak, Anna and Sponring, Andreas and Schmid, Thomas and Zelger, Bettina and Ager, Clemens and Klodzinska, Ewa and Denz, Hubert and Pizzini, Alex and Jamnig, Herbert and Amann, Anton and Lucciarini, Paolo and Troppmair, Jakob (2013),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24862102&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Comparative analyses of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) from patients, tumors and transformed cell lines for the validation of lung cancer-derived breath markers.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;Cancer Epidemiology, Biomarkers &amp;amp; Prevention (8)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.&lt;sup&gt;1088&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;1752&lt;/sub&gt;-7155/8/2/027111&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breath analysis for the purpose of non-invasive diagnosis of lung cancer has yielded numerous candidate compounds with still questionable clinical relevance. To arrive at suitable volatile organic compounds our approach combined the analysis of different sources: isolated tumor samples compared to healthy lung tissues, and exhaled breath from lung cancer patients and healthy controls. Candidate compounds were further compared to substances previously identified in the comparison of transformed and normal lung epithelial cell lines. For human studies, a breath sampling device was developed enabling automated and CO2-controlled collection of the end-tidal air. All samples were first preconcentrated on multibed sorption tubes and analyzed with gas chromatography mass spectrometry (GC-MS). Significantly (p &amp;lt; 0.05) higher concentrations in all three types of cancer samples studied were observed for ethanol and n-octane. Additional metabolites (inter alia 2-methylpentane, n-hexane) significantly released by lung cancer cells were observed at higher levels in cancer lung tissues and breath samples (compared to respective healthy controls) with statistical significance (p &amp;lt; 0.05) only in breath samples. The results obtained confirmed the cancer-related origin of volatile metabolites, e.g. ethanol and octane that were both detected at significantly (p &amp;lt; 0.05) elevated concentrations in all three kinds of cancer samples studied. This work is an important step towards identification of volatile breath markers of lung cancer through the demonstration of cancer-related origin of certain volatile metabolites.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Capillary-Column Proton-Transfer-Reaction Time-of-Flight Mass Spectrometry</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/ruzsanyi2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/ruzsanyi2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ruzsanyi, Veronika and Fischer, Lukas and Herbig, Jens and Ager, Clemens and Amann, Anton (2013),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0021967313015392 http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24119758&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Multi-Capillary-Column Proton-Transfer-Reaction Time-of-Flight Mass Spectrometry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;Journal of Chromatography A (1316)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.1016/j.chroma.2013.09.072&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proton-transfer-reaction time-of-flight mass-spectrometry (PTR-TOFMS) exhibits high selectivity with a resolution of around 5000m/$\Delta$m. While isobars can be separated with this resolution, discrimination of isomeric compounds is usually not possible. The coupling of a multi-capillary column (MCC) with a PTR-TOFMS overcomes these problems as demonstrated in this paper for the ketone isomers 3-heptanone and 2-methyl-3-hexanone and for different aldehydes. Moreover, fragmentation of compounds can be studied in detail which might even improve the identification. LODs for compounds tested are in the range of low ppbv and peak positions of the respective separated substances show good repeatability (RSD of the peak positions &amp;lt;3.2\%). Due to its special characteristics, such as isothermal operation, compact size, the MCC setup is suitable to be installed inside the instrument and the overall retention time for a complete spectrum is only a few minutes: this allows near real-time measurements in the optional MCC mode. In contrast to other methods that yield additional separation, such as the use of pre-cursor ions other than H3O(+), this method yields additional information without increasing complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of volatile metabolites taken up by or released from Streptococcus pneumoniae and Haemophilus influenzae by using GC-MS.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2012d/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2012d/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Filipiak, Wojciech and Sponring, Andreas and Bauer, Maria and AGER, Clemens and FILIPIAK, Anna and WIESENHOFER, Helmut and NAGL, Markus and Troppmair, Jakob and Amann, Anton and Baur, Maria M and AGER, Clemens and FILIPIAK, Anna and WIESENHOFER, Helmut and NAGL, Markus and Troppmair, Jakob and Amann, Anton (2012),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23059976 http://cat.inist.fr/?aModele=afficheN&amp;amp;cpsidt=26727487&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Characterization of volatile metabolites taken up by or released from Streptococcus pneumoniae and Haemophilus influenzae by using GC-MS.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;Microbiology (Reading, England) (158)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.1099/mic.0.062687-0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volatile organic compounds (VOCs) released from or taken up by Streptococcus pneumoniae and Haemophilus influenzae cultures were analysed by means of GC-MS after adsorption of headspace samples on multi-bed sorption tubes. Sampling was performed at different time points during cultivation of bacteria to follow the dynamics of VOC metabolism. VOCs were identified not only by spectral library match but also based on retention times of native standards. As many as 34 volatile metabolites were released from S. pneumoniae and 28 from H. influenzae, comprising alcohols, aldehydes, esters, hydrocarbons, ketones and sulfur-containing compounds. For both species, acetic acid, acetaldehyde, methyl methacrylate, 2,3-butanedione and methanethiol were found in strongly elevated concentrations and 1-butanol and butanal in moderately elevated concentrations. In addition, characteristic volatile biomarkers were detected for both bacterial species and exclusively for S. pneumoniae, also catabolism of aldehydes (3-methylbutanal and hexanal) was found. The results obtained provide important input into the knowledge about volatile bacterial biomarkers, which may become particularly important for detection of pathogens in upper airways by breath-gas analysis in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dependence of exhaled breath composition on exogenous factors, smoking habits and exposure to air pollutants</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2012b/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2012b/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Filipiak, Wojciech and Ruzsanyi, Veronika and Mochalski, Paweł and Filipiak, Anna and Bajtarevic, Amel and Ager, Clemens and Denz, Hubert and Hilbe, Wolfgang and Jamnig, Herbert and Hackl, Martin and Dzien, Alexander and Amann, Anton (2012),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://iopscience.iop.org/1752-7163/6/3/036008/ http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22932429&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dependence of exhaled breath composition on exogenous factors, smoking habits and exposure to air pollutants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;Journal of Breath Research (6)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.&lt;sup&gt;1088&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;1752&lt;/sub&gt;-7155/6/3/036008&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-invasive disease monitoring on the basis of volatile breath markers is a very attractive but challenging task. Several hundreds of compounds have been detected in exhaled air using modern analytical techniques (e.g. proton-transfer reaction mass spectrometry, gas chromatography-mass spectrometry) and have even been linked to various diseases. However, the biochemical background for most of compounds detected in breath samples has not been elucidated; therefore, the obtained results should be interpreted with care to avoid false correlations. The major aim of this study was to assess the effects of smoking on the composition of exhaled breath. Additionally, the potential origin of breath volatile organic compounds (VOCs) is discussed focusing on diet, environmental exposure and biological pathways based on other&amp;rsquo;s studies. Profiles of VOCs detected in exhaled breath and inspired air samples of 115 subjects with addition of urine headspace derived from 50 volunteers are presented. Samples were analyzed with GC-MS after preconcentration on multibed sorption tubes in case of breath samples and solid phase micro-extraction (SPME) in the case of urine samples. Altogether 266 compounds were found in exhaled breath of at least 10\% of the volunteers. From these, 162 compounds were identified by spectral library match and retention time (based on reference standards). It is shown that the composition of exhaled breath is considerably influenced by exposure to pollution and indoor-air contaminants and particularly by smoking. More than 80 organic compounds were found to be significantly related to smoking, the largest group comprising unsaturated hydrocarbons (29 dienes, 27 alkenes and 3 alkynes). On the basis of the presented results, we suggest that for the future understanding of breath data it will be necessary to carefully investigate the potential biological origin of volatiles, e.g., by means of analysis of tissues, isolated cell lines or other body fluids. In particular, VOCs linked to smoking habit or being the results of human exposure should be considered with care for clinical diagnosis since small changes in their concentration profiles (typically in the ppt(v)-ppb(v) range) revealing that the outbreak of certain disease might be hampered by already high background.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Molecular analysis of volatile metabolites released specifically by Staphylococcus aureus and Pseudomonas aeruginosa.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2012a/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2012a/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Filipiak, Wojciech and Sponring, Andreas and Bauer, Maria and Filipiak, Anna and Ager, Clemens and Wiesenhofer, Helmut and Nagl, Markus and Troppmair, Jakob and Amann, Anton and Baur, Maria Magdalena and Filipiak, Anna and Ager, Clemens and Wiesenhofer, Helmut and Nagl, Markus and Troppmair, Jakob and Amann, Anton (2012),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=3444334&amp;amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;amp;rendertype=abstract http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22716902&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Molecular analysis of volatile metabolites released specifically by Staphylococcus aureus and Pseudomonas aeruginosa.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;BMC microbiology (12)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.&lt;sup&gt;1186&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;1471&lt;/sub&gt;-2180-12-113&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ABSTRACT: BACKGROUND: The routinely used microbiological diagnosis of ventilator associated pneumonia (VAP) is time consuming and often requires invasive methods for collection of human specimens (e.g. bronchoscopy). Therefore, it is of utmost interest to develop a non-invasive method for the early detection of bacterial infection in ventilated patients, preferably allowing the identification of the specific pathogens. The present work is an attempt to identify pathogen-derived volatile biomarkers in breath that can be used for early and non-invasive diagnosis of ventilator associated pneumonia (VAP). For this purpose, in vitro experiments with bacteria most frequently found in VAP patients, i.e. Staphylococcus aureus and Pseudomonas aeruginosa, were performed to investigate the release or consumption of volatile organic compounds (VOCs). RESULTS: Headspace samples were collected and preconcentrated on multibed sorption tubes at different time points and subsequently analyzed with gas chromatography mass spectrometry (GC-MS). As many as 32 and 37 volatile metabolites were released by S. aureus and P. aeruginosa, respectively. Distinct differences in the bacteria-specific VOC profiles were found, especially with regard to aldehydes (e.g. acetaldehyde, 3-methylbutanal), which were taken up only by P. aeruginosa but released by S. aureus. Differences in concentration profiles were also found for acids (e.g. isovaleric acid), ketones (e.g. acetoin, 2-nonanone), hydrocarbons (e.g. 2-butene, 1,10-undecadiene), alcohols (e.g. 2-methyl-1-propanol, 2-butanol), esters (e.g. ethyl formate, methyl 2-methylbutyrate), volatile sulfur compounds (VSCs, e.g. dimethylsulfide) and volatile nitrogen compounds (VNCs, e.g. 3-methylpyrrole). Importantly, a significant VOC release was found already 1.5 hours after culture start, corresponding to cell numbers of ~{}8*106 [CFUs/ml]. CONCLUSIONS: The results obtained provide strong evidence that the detection and perhaps even identification of bacteria could be achieved by determination of characteristic volatile metabolites, supporting the clinical use of breath-gas analysis as non-invasive method for early detection of bacterial lung infections.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimization of sampling parameters for collection and preconcentration of alveolar air by needle traps.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Filipiak, Wojciech and Filipiak, Anna and Ager, Clemens and Wiesenhofer, Helmut and Amann, Anton (2012),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22621839&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Optimization of sampling parameters for collection and preconcentration of alveolar air by needle traps.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;Journal of breath research (6)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.&lt;sup&gt;1088&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;1752&lt;/sub&gt;-7155/6/2/027107&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The approach for breath-VOCs&amp;rsquo; collection and preconcentration by applying needle traps was developed and optimized. The alveolar air was collected from only a few exhalations under visual control of expired CO(2) into a large gas-tight glass syringe and then warmed up to 45 °C for a short time to avoid condensation. Subsequently, a specially constructed sampling device equipped with Bronkhorst® electronic flow controllers was used for automated adsorption. This sampling device allows time-saving collection of expired/inspired air in parallel onto three different needle traps as well as improvement of sensitivity and reproducibility of NT-GC-MS analysis by collection of relatively large (up to 150 ml) volume of exhaled breath. It was shown that the collection of alveolar air derived from only a few exhalations into a large syringe followed by automated adsorption on needle traps yields better results than manual sorption by up/down cycles with a 1 ml syringe, mostly due to avoided condensation and electronically controlled stable sample flow rate. The optimal profile and composition of needle traps consists of 2 cm Carbopack X and 1 cm Carboxen 1000, allowing highly efficient VOCs&amp;rsquo; enrichment, while injection by a fast expansive flow technique requires no modifications in instrumentation and fully automated GC-MS analysis can be performed with a commercially available autosampler. This optimized analytical procedure considerably facilitates the collection and enrichment of alveolar air, and is therefore suitable for application at the bedside of critically ill patients in an intensive care unit. Due to its simplicity it can replace the time-consuming sampling of sufficient breath volume by numerous up/down cycles with a 1 ml syringe.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temporal profiling of human urine VOCs and its potential role under the ruins of collapsed buildings.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/mochalski2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/mochalski2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mochalski, Paweł and Krapf, Karin and Ager, Clemens and Wiesenhofer, Helmut and Agapiou, Agapios and Statheropoulos, Milt and Fuchs, Dietmar and Ellmerer, Ernst and Buszewski, Bogusław and Amann, Anton (2012),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22482743&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Temporal profiling of human urine VOCs and its potential role under the ruins of collapsed buildings.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;Toxicology mechanisms and methods (22)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.&lt;sup&gt;3109&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;15376516&lt;/sub&gt;.2012.682664&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Context: The scent profile of human urine was investigated as potential source of chemical markers of human presence in collapsed buildings after natural or man-made disasters. Objective: The main goals of this study were to build a library of potential biomarkers of human urine to be used for the detection of entrapped victims and to further examine their evolution profile in time. Materials and methods: Headspace solid-phase microextraction-gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (HS-SPME-GC-MS) was used to detect and identify the volatile organic compounds (VOCs) spontaneously released from urine of 20 healthy volunteers. Additionally, the evolution of human urine headspace during four days storage at room temperature was investigated. Results: 33 omnipresent species with incidence higher than 80\% were selected as potential urine markers. The most represented chemical classes were ketones with 10 representatives, aldehydes (7 species) and sulfur compounds (7 species). The monitoring of the evolution of the urine scent demonstrated an increase in the emission of 26 omnipresent urinary volatiles (rise from 36\% to 526\%). The highest increase was noted for dimethyldisulfide and dimethyltrisulfide (fivefold increase) and 3-methyl-2-butanone, 4-methyl-2-pentanone and 3-hexanone (fourfold rise). Only three compounds exhibited decreasing trend; dimethylsulfone, octanal and propanal. Conclusion: The ubiquitous urine VOCs identified within this study create a library of potential markers of human urine to be verified in further field studies, involving portable and sensitive instruments, directly applied in the field.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of exhaled breath for screening of lung cancer patients</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/amann2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/amann2010/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Amann, Anton and Ligor, Magdalena and Ligor, Tomasz and Bajtarevic, Amel and Ager, Clemens and Pienz, Martin and Denz, Hubert and Fiegl, Michael and Hilbe, Wolfgang and Weiss, Wolfgang and Lukas, Peter and Jamnig, Herbert and Hackl, Martin and Haidenberger, Alfred and Sponring, Andreas and Filipiak, Wojciech and Miekisch, Wolfram and Schubert, Jochen K and Troppmair, Jakob and Buszewski, Bogusław (2010),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springerlink.com/index/2G4G4271214G2057.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Analysis of exhaled breath for screening of lung cancer patients&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;memo-Magazine of (memo(2010))&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.1007/s12254-010-0219-2s12254-010-0219-2&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) in the headspace of NCI-H1666 lung cancer cells.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/sponring2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/sponring2010/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sponring, Andreas and Filipiak, Wojciech and Ager, Clemens and Schubert, Jochen K and Miekisch, Wolfram and Amann, Anton and Troppmair, Jakob (2010),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21263191&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Analysis of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) in the headspace of NCI-H1666 lung cancer cells.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;Cancer biomarkers : section A of Disease markers (7)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.3233/CBM-2010-0182&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysis of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) provides an elegant approach for cancer screening and disease monitoring, whose use is currently limited by a lack of validated cancer-derived metabolites, which may serve as biomarkers. The aim of the experiments presented here was to investigate the release and consumption of VOCs from the non small cell lung cancer cell line NCI-H1666, which was originally derived from a bronchoalveolar carcinoma.Following detachment by trypsinization suspended cells were incubated in a sealed fermenter for 21 hours. 200 ml of headspace from the cell culture were sampled, diluted with dry, highly purified air and preconcentrated by adsorption on three different solid sorbents with increasing adsorption strength. VOC-analysis was performed by thermodesorption-gas chromatography mass spectrometry (TD-GC-MS). In contrast to our previous studies experiments with NCI-H1666 cells only confirmed the consumption of several aldehydes, n-butyl acetate and the ethers methyl tert-butyl ether and ethyl tert-butyl ether, but no unequivocal release of VOCs was observed. Together with our previously published work these data indicate that the consumption of certain VOCs is commonly observed while their release shows cell line-restricted patterns, whose underlying causes are unknown.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TD-GC-MS analysis of volatile metabolites of human lung cancer and normal cells in vitro.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.gitlab.io/bdcaf/coauthored/filipiak2010/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Filipiak, Wojciech and Sponring, Andreas and Filipiak, Anna and Ager, Clemens and Schubert, Jochen K and Miekisch, Wolfram and Amann, Anton and Troppmair, Jakob (2010),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20056637&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;TD-GC-MS analysis of volatile metabolites of human lung cancer and normal cells in vitro.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;Cancer epidemiology, biomarkers &amp;amp; prevention : a publication of the American Association for Cancer Research, cosponsored by the American Society of Preventive Oncology (19)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.&lt;sup&gt;1158&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;1055&lt;/sub&gt;-9965.EPI-09-0162&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of this study was to confirm the existence of volatile organic compounds (VOC) specifically released or consumed by the lung cancer cell line A549, which could be used in future screens as biomarkers for the early detection of lung cancer. For comparison, primary human bronchial epithelial cells (HBEpC) and human fibroblasts (hFB) were included. VOCs were detected in the headspace of cell cultures or medium controls following adsorption on solid sorbents, thermodesorption, and analysis by gas chromatography mass spectrometry. Using this approach, we identified VOCs that behaved similarly in normal and transformed cells. Thus, concentrations of 2-pentanone and 2,4-dimethyl-1-heptene were found to increase in the headspace of A549, HBEpC, and hFB cell cultures. In addition, the ethers methyl tert-butyl ether and ethyl tert-butyl ether could be detected at elevated levels in the case of A549 cells and one of the untransformed cell lines. However, especially branched hydrocarbons and alcohols were seen increased more frequently in untransformed than A549 cells. A big variety of predominantly aldehydes and the ester n-butyl acetate were found at decreased concentrations in the headspace of all cell lines tested compared with medium controls. Again, more different aldehydes were found to be decreased in hFB and HBEpC cells compared with A549 cells and 2-butenal was metabolized exclusively by both control cell lines. These data suggest that certain groups of VOCs may be preferentially associated with the transformed phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
