<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on C. Ager</title>
    <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on C. Ager</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Clemens Ager, Brixlegg</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 08:51:41 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://bdcaf.github.io/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Makey Makey</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/11/05/makey-makey/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 08:51:41 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/11/05/makey-makey/</guid>
      <description>I am quite confident using make to create complex reports. As I dig into R I see they have an interesting work flow creating packages. It addresses a few important issues - tracking dependent packages, documenting stuff and testing. Most important packaging and installing on other systems can be done automatically using a single command. I want that.
I found Makefiles mentioned several times included in the documentation - but so far haven&amp;rsquo;t figured out how they are supposed to be used.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Package rawTof</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/08/05/package-rawtof/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2017 17:51:52 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/08/05/package-rawtof/</guid>
      <description>I have just released a simple package to read PTR-TOF h5 files. This used to be part of a larger project on developing a pipeline for working with PTR-TOF files, but stripped from all experimental functions. The other package should become a paper, so hold on for that.
The package can be found at bdcaf/rawTof.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publication word cloud</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/01/19/publication-word-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 12:56:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/2017/01/19/publication-word-cloud/</guid>
      <description>I wanted to play with word clouds for some time. Usually the problem is to obtain a nice corpus. Luckily PubMedWordCloud was recently updated and I had something to play with.
The initial cloud looks not good enough - I did not like how plurals are counted separately. Since I couldn&amp;rsquo;t clean it up easy enough I ended up going back to the tm package and roll my own script. Unfortunately it&amp;rsquo;s far from publishable.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>