<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Coauthoreds on C. Ager</title>
    <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Coauthoreds on C. Ager</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>Clemens Ager, Brixlegg</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>test</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2016/</guid>
      <description>Filipiak, Wojciech and Beer, Ronny and Sponring, Andreas and Filipiak, Anna and Ager, Clemens and Schiefecker, Alois and Lanthaler, Simon and Helbok, Raimund and Nagl, Markus and Troppmair, Jakob and Amann, Anton (2015), Breath analysis for in vivo detection of pathogens related to ventilator-associated pneumonia in intensive care patients: a prospective pilot study , Journal of Breath Research (9), doi: 10.1088&amp;frasl;1752-7155/9/1/016004</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breath analysis for in vivo detection of pathogens related to ventilator-associated pneumonia in intensive care patients: A prospective pilot study</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2015a/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2015 10:36:21 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2015a/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/270513085_Breath_analysis_for_in_vivo_detection_of_pathogens_related_to_ventilator-associated_pneumonia_in_intensive_care_patients_A_prospective_pilot_study&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;research gate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wojciech Filipiak, Ronny Beer , Andreas Sponring , Anna Filipiak, Clemens Ager, Alois Schiefecker, Simon Lanthaler , Raimund Helbok , Markus Nagl , Jakob Troppmair and Anton Amann&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breath analysis for in vivo detection of pathogens related to ventilator-associated pneumonia in intensive care patients: a prospective pilot study</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2015/</guid>
      <description>Filipiak, Wojciech and Beer, Ronny and Sponring, Andreas and Filipiak, Anna and Ager, Clemens and Schiefecker, Alois and Lanthaler, Simon and Helbok, Raimund and Nagl, Markus and Troppmair, Jakob and Amann, Anton (2015), Breath analysis for in vivo detection of pathogens related to ventilator-associated pneumonia in intensive care patients: a prospective pilot study , Journal of Breath Research (9), doi: 10.1088&amp;frasl;1752-7155/9/1/016004</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative analyses of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) from patients, tumors and transformed cell lines for the validation of lung cancer-derived breath markers.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Filipiak, Wojciech and Filipiak, Anna and Sponring, Andreas and Schmid, Thomas and Zelger, Bettina and Ager, Clemens and Klodzinska, Ewa and Denz, Hubert and Pizzini, Alex and Lucciarini, Paolo and Jamnig, Herbert and Troppmair, Jakob and Amann, Anton (2014),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24862102&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Comparative analyses of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) from patients, tumors and transformed cell lines for the validation of lung cancer-derived breath markers.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;Journal of breath research (8)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.&lt;sup&gt;1088&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;1752&lt;/sub&gt;-7155/8/2/027111&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ABA-Cloud: support for collaborative breath research.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/elsayed2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/elsayed2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elsayed, Ibrahim and Ludescher, Thomas and King, Julian and Ager, Clemens and Trosin, Michael and Senocak, Uygar and Brezany, Peter and Feilhauer, Thomas and Amann, Anton (2013),
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23619467&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ABA-Cloud: support for collaborative breath research.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ,
&lt;em&gt;Journal of breath research (7)&lt;/em&gt;,
doi: 10.&lt;sup&gt;1088&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;1752&lt;/sub&gt;-7155/7/2/026007&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative analyses of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) from patients, tumors and transformed cell lines for the validation of lung cancer-derived breath markers.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2013/</guid>
      <description>Filipiak, Wojciech and Filipiak, Anna and Sponring, Andreas and Schmid, Thomas and Zelger, Bettina and Ager, Clemens and Klodzinska, Ewa and Denz, Hubert and Pizzini, Alex and Jamnig, Herbert and Amann, Anton and Lucciarini, Paolo and Troppmair, Jakob (2013), Comparative analyses of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) from patients, tumors and transformed cell lines for the validation of lung cancer-derived breath markers. , Cancer Epidemiology, Biomarkers &amp;amp; Prevention (8), doi: 10.1088&amp;frasl;1752-7155/8/2/027111</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Capillary-Column Proton-Transfer-Reaction Time-of-Flight Mass Spectrometry</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/ruzsanyi2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/ruzsanyi2013/</guid>
      <description>Ruzsanyi, Veronika and Fischer, Lukas and Herbig, Jens and Ager, Clemens and Amann, Anton (2013), Multi-Capillary-Column Proton-Transfer-Reaction Time-of-Flight Mass Spectrometry , Journal of Chromatography A (1316), doi: 10.1016/j.chroma.2013.09.072
Proton-transfer-reaction time-of-flight mass-spectrometry (PTR-TOFMS) exhibits high selectivity with a resolution of around 5000m/$\Delta$m. While isobars can be separated with this resolution, discrimination of isomeric compounds is usually not possible. The coupling of a multi-capillary column (MCC) with a PTR-TOFMS overcomes these problems as demonstrated in this paper for the ketone isomers 3-heptanone and 2-methyl-3-hexanone and for different aldehydes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of volatile metabolites taken up by or released from Streptococcus pneumoniae and Haemophilus influenzae by using GC-MS.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2012d/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2012d/</guid>
      <description>Filipiak, Wojciech and Sponring, Andreas and Bauer, Maria and AGER, Clemens and FILIPIAK, Anna and WIESENHOFER, Helmut and NAGL, Markus and Troppmair, Jakob and Amann, Anton and Baur, Maria M and AGER, Clemens and FILIPIAK, Anna and WIESENHOFER, Helmut and NAGL, Markus and Troppmair, Jakob and Amann, Anton (2012), Characterization of volatile metabolites taken up by or released from Streptococcus pneumoniae and Haemophilus influenzae by using GC-MS. , Microbiology (Reading, England) (158), doi: 10.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dependence of exhaled breath composition on exogenous factors, smoking habits and exposure to air pollutants</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2012b/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2012b/</guid>
      <description>Filipiak, Wojciech and Ruzsanyi, Veronika and Mochalski, Paweł and Filipiak, Anna and Bajtarevic, Amel and Ager, Clemens and Denz, Hubert and Hilbe, Wolfgang and Jamnig, Herbert and Hackl, Martin and Dzien, Alexander and Amann, Anton (2012), Dependence of exhaled breath composition on exogenous factors, smoking habits and exposure to air pollutants , Journal of Breath Research (6), doi: 10.1088&amp;frasl;1752-7155/6/3/036008
Non-invasive disease monitoring on the basis of volatile breath markers is a very attractive but challenging task.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Molecular analysis of volatile metabolites released specifically by Staphylococcus aureus and Pseudomonas aeruginosa.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2012a/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2012a/</guid>
      <description>Filipiak, Wojciech and Sponring, Andreas and Bauer, Maria and Filipiak, Anna and Ager, Clemens and Wiesenhofer, Helmut and Nagl, Markus and Troppmair, Jakob and Amann, Anton (2012) Molecular analysis of volatile metabolites released specifically by Staphylococcus aureus and Pseudomonas aeruginosa. , BMC microbiology (12), doi: 10.1186&amp;frasl;1471-2180-12-113
ABSTRACT: BACKGROUND: The routinely used microbiological diagnosis of ventilator associated pneumonia (VAP) is time consuming and often requires invasive methods for collection of human specimens (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimization of sampling parameters for collection and preconcentration of alveolar air by needle traps.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2012/</guid>
      <description>Filipiak, Wojciech and Filipiak, Anna and Ager, Clemens and Wiesenhofer, Helmut and Amann, Anton (2012), Optimization of sampling parameters for collection and preconcentration of alveolar air by needle traps. , Journal of breath research (6), doi: 10.1088&amp;frasl;1752-7155/6/2/027107
The approach for breath-VOCs&amp;rsquo; collection and preconcentration by applying needle traps was developed and optimized. The alveolar air was collected from only a few exhalations under visual control of expired CO(2) into a large gas-tight glass syringe and then warmed up to 45 °C for a short time to avoid condensation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temporal profiling of human urine VOCs and its potential role under the ruins of collapsed buildings.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/mochalski2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/mochalski2012/</guid>
      <description>Mochalski, Paweł and Krapf, Karin and Ager, Clemens and Wiesenhofer, Helmut and Agapiou, Agapios and Statheropoulos, Milt and Fuchs, Dietmar and Ellmerer, Ernst and Buszewski, Bogusław and Amann, Anton (2012), Temporal profiling of human urine VOCs and its potential role under the ruins of collapsed buildings. , Toxicology mechanisms and methods (22), doi: 10.3109&amp;frasl;15376516.2012.682664
Context: The scent profile of human urine was investigated as potential source of chemical markers of human presence in collapsed buildings after natural or man-made disasters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of exhaled breath for screening of lung cancer patients</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/amann2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/amann2010/</guid>
      <description>Amann, Anton and Ligor, Magdalena and Ligor, Tomasz and Bajtarevic, Amel and Ager, Clemens and Pienz, Martin and Denz, Hubert and Fiegl, Michael and Hilbe, Wolfgang and Weiss, Wolfgang and Lukas, Peter and Jamnig, Herbert and Hackl, Martin and Haidenberger, Alfred and Sponring, Andreas and Filipiak, Wojciech and Miekisch, Wolfram and Schubert, Jochen K and Troppmair, Jakob and Buszewski, Bogusław (2010), Analysis of exhaled breath for screening of lung cancer patients , memo-Magazine of (memo(2010)), doi: 10.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) in the headspace of NCI-H1666 lung cancer cells.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/sponring2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/sponring2010/</guid>
      <description>Sponring, Andreas and Filipiak, Wojciech and Ager, Clemens and Schubert, Jochen K and Miekisch, Wolfram and Amann, Anton and Troppmair, Jakob (2010), Analysis of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) in the headspace of NCI-H1666 lung cancer cells. , Cancer biomarkers : section A of Disease markers (7), doi: 10.3233/CBM-2010-0182
Analysis of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) provides an elegant approach for cancer screening and disease monitoring, whose use is currently limited by a lack of validated cancer-derived metabolites, which may serve as biomarkers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TD-GC-MS analysis of volatile metabolites of human lung cancer and normal cells in vitro.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2010/</guid>
      <description>Filipiak, Wojciech and Sponring, Andreas and Filipiak, Anna and Ager, Clemens and Schubert, Jochen K and Miekisch, Wolfram and Amann, Anton and Troppmair, Jakob (2010), TD-GC-MS analysis of volatile metabolites of human lung cancer and normal cells in vitro. , Cancer epidemiology, biomarkers &amp;amp; prevention : a publication of the American Association for Cancer Research, cosponsored by the American Society of Preventive Oncology (19), doi: 10.1158&amp;frasl;1055-9965.EPI-09-0162
The aim of this study was to confirm the existence of volatile organic compounds (VOC) specifically released or consumed by the lung cancer cell line A549, which could be used in future screens as biomarkers for the early detection of lung cancer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of Proton Transfer Reaction-Mass Spectrometry and Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry in Analysis of Breath Samples</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/ligor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/ligor/</guid>
      <description>Ligor, Tomasz and Ager, Clemens and Schwarz, Konrad Eugen and Zebrowski, Wojciech and Amann, Anton and Buszewski, Bogusław (2009), Comparison of Proton Transfer Reaction-Mass Spectrometry and Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry in Analysis of Breath Samples , Chemia analityczna (54), doi:
Proton transfer reaction-mass spectrometry (PTR-MS) and gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) methods were compared and used for determination of volatile organic compounds in breath of patients suffering from COPD (chronic obstructive pulmonary disease).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Determination of volatile organic compounds in exhaled breath of patients with lung cancer using solid phase microextraction and gas chromatography mass spectrometry</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/ligora/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/ligora/</guid>
      <description>Ligor, Magdalena and Ligor, Tomasz and Bajtarevic, Amel and Ager, Clemens and Pienz, Martin and Klieber, Martin and Denz, Hubert and Fiegl, Michael and Hilbe, Wolfgang and Weiss, Wolfgang and Lukas, Peter and Jamnig, Herbert and Hackl, Martin and Buszewski, Bogusław and Miekisch, Wolfram and Schubert, Jochen K and Amann, Anton (2009), Determination of volatile organic compounds in exhaled breath of patients with lung cancer using solid phase microextraction and gas chromatography mass spectrometry , Clinical chemistry and laboratory medicine (47), doi:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Noninvasive detection of lung cancer by analysis of exhaled breath.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/bajtarevic2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/bajtarevic2009/</guid>
      <description>Bajtarevic, Amel and Ager, Clemens and Pienz, Martin and Klieber, Martin and Schwarz, Konrad Eugen and Ligor, Magdalena and Ligor, Tomasz and Filipiak, Wojciech and Denz, Hubert and Fiegl, Michael and Hilbe, Wolfgang and Weiss, Wolfgang and Lukas, Peter and Jamnig, Herbert and Hackl, Martin and Haidenberger, Alfred and Buszewski, Bogusław and Miekisch, Wolfram and Schubert, Jochen K and Amann, Anton (2009), Noninvasive detection of lung cancer by analysis of exhaled breath.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release of volatile organic compounds from the lung cancer cell line NCI-H2087 in vitro</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/sponring2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/sponring2009/</guid>
      <description>Sponring, Andreas and Filipiak, Wojciech and Mikoviny, Tomas and Ager, Clemens and Schubert, Jochen and Miekisch, Wolfram and Amann, Anton and Troppmair, Jakob (2009), Release of volatile organic compounds from the lung cancer cell line NCI-H2087 in vitro , Anticancer (29), doi:
AIM: The aim of this work was to confirm the existence of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) specifically released by lung cancer cells. MATERIALS AND METHODS: NCI-H2087 cells were trypsinized and 100 x 10(6) cells were incubated in a sealed fermenter overnight.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) from the lung cancer cell line CALU-1 in vitro.</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2008/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/filipiak2008/</guid>
      <description>Filipiak, Wojciech and Sponring, Andreas and Mikoviny, Tomas and Ager, Clemens and Schubert, Jochen K and Miekisch, Wolfram and Amann, Anton and Troppmair, Jakob (2008), Release of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) from the lung cancer cell line CALU-1 in vitro. , Cancer Cell International (8), doi: 10.1186&amp;frasl;1475-2867-8-17
BACKGROUND: The aim of this work was to confirm the existence of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) specifically released or consumed by lung cancer cells.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The analysis of healthy volunteers&#39; exhaled breath by the use of solid-phase microextraction and GC-MS</title>
      <link>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/ligor2008/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bdcaf.github.io/coauthored/ligor2008/</guid>
      <description>Ligor, Tomasz and Ligor, Magdalena and Amann, Anton and Ager, Clemens and Bachler, Miriam and Dzien, Alexander and Buszewski, Bogusław (2008), The analysis of healthy volunteers&amp;rsquo; exhaled breath by the use of solid-phase microextraction and GC-MS , Journal of Breath Research (2), doi: 10.1088&amp;frasl;1752-7155/2/4/046006
We analysed breath and inhaled room air samples from 39 healthy volunteers (28 non-smokers, 8 smokers and 3 ex-smokers) by SPME-GC-MS. Mixed expiratory and indoor air samples were collected in freshly cleaned Tedlar bags.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>